<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>book-review on tobilehman.com:~</title>
    <link>https://tobilehman.com/tags/book-review/</link>
    <description>Recent content in book-review on tobilehman.com:~</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2010-2023 Tobi Lehman. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 21:10:35 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://tobilehman.com/tags/book-review/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Time Loops</title>
      <link>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-time-loops/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 21:10:35 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-time-loops/</guid>
      <description>The book Time Loops by Eric Wargo makes a careful argument for the reality of precognitive dreams.&#xA;My personal interest in this topic has to do with my obsession with time and to an extent, time travel.&#xA;The author starts the book by summarizing a number of examples of dreams that came true, and closely studies an early dream pioneer named J.W. Dunne who wrote An Experiment with Time. What stands out about Dunne is how he made the distinction between dreaming about events out in the world vs events as experienced by the future self.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Where&#39;s My Flying Car?</title>
      <link>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-wheres-my-flying-car/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 12:49:54 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-wheres-my-flying-car/</guid>
      <description>This book has two parts, one looks back and asks why flying cars never came to market, and the other looks forward to what possibilities lay ahead. The author has a background in chip design and nanotechnology, and even became a pilot so he could better evaluate the feasibility of flying car designs.&#xA;The autogyro, developed in the 1930s by Juan de la Cierva, was a promising candidate for a flying car.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Technological Revolutions and Financial Capital</title>
      <link>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-perez-trfc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 06:45:23 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-perez-trfc/</guid>
      <description>This book develops a theory of a cyclical pattern in the economy. The pattern describes how certain new technologies spread to become a whole new way of structuring society. The author Carlota Perez calls this a technological revolution and it&amp;rsquo;s associated &amp;ldquo;techno-economic paradigm&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;In this review I want to summarize her theory using less jargon. Even though the book reads like an academic text, and the jargon is used consistently, I want to dig into the idea in more common language.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Atomic Habits</title>
      <link>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-atomic-habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 14:19:20 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-atomic-habits/</guid>
      <description>Atomic Habits is written so clearly that I have a hard time believing &amp;lsquo;James Clear&amp;rsquo; isn&amp;rsquo;t a clever pen name. That clarity comes from experience and practice. His story about recovering from a major head injury and returning to sports is inspiring. His recovery is a big source of practical knowledge about how to build good habits.&#xA;Before I read this, I thought of habits using the goal/discipline model. You start by setting a goal, then you apply discipline in doing something repeatedly to reach that goal.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Working in Public</title>
      <link>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-working-in-public/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 21:22:39 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-working-in-public/</guid>
      <description>The story of open source software most of us believe is wrong. The production of open source software isn&amp;rsquo;t like some egalitarian commune, it&amp;rsquo;s driven mostly by a few individuals. Through analyzing git commit frequency distributions and interviewing prominent open source contributors and maintainers, Nadia Eghbal captures the living history of open source software.&#xA;In addition, she also analyses the main problems of maintenance that threaten the long term sustainability of open source software.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
