<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Computing on tlehman@home</title>
    <link>/categories/computing/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Computing on tlehman@home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/computing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Point Time Machine at any destination</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/12/08/point-time-machine-at-any-destination/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/12/08/point-time-machine-at-any-destination/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;set-up-time-machine-on-mac-os-x-to-back-up-to-any-network-volume&#34;&gt;Set up Time Machine (on Mac OS X) to back up to any network volume&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time Machine is a fine backup solution if you have a dedicated external hard drive, or if you have no problem with paying for a specialized Time Capsule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a network volume, such as an NFS, CIFS, AFP, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/philipl/pifs#readme&#34;&gt;πfs&lt;/a&gt; share on a file server, you need to configure a few things in order for Time Machine to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/5691649/an-easier-way-to-set-up-time-machine-to-back-up-to-a-networked-windows-computer&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; which gives step-by-step instructions, but it involves executing some shell commands. I&amp;rsquo;ve distilled it into three scripts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1_enable_network_volumes.sh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2_make_image.sh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3_set_destination.sh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-1&#34;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clone &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tlehman/time_machine_any_destination&#34;&gt;this repository&lt;/a&gt;, and execute this script by cd-ing to the repository&amp;rsquo;s directory, and run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;./1_enable_network_volumes.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explanation:&lt;/em&gt; This enables unsupported network volumes by setting &lt;code&gt;TMShowUnsupportedNetworkVolumes&lt;/code&gt; to 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-2&#34;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, you need to prepare a special directory on your network share, this second script will do that for you. Make sure you have your network share &lt;code&gt;/your/network/share&lt;/code&gt; ready, and choose a maximum number of gigabytes, say &lt;code&gt;216&lt;/code&gt;, and run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;./2_make_image.sh 216 /your/network/share
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning&lt;/strong&gt;: This script will take a while, you&amp;rsquo;ll know when it&amp;rsquo;s done when you &lt;code&gt;Finished! Happy backups!&lt;/code&gt; in your terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explanation&lt;/em&gt;: This script creates a disk image &lt;code&gt;name.sparsebundle&lt;/code&gt;, where name is your computer name, the result of the command &lt;code&gt;scutil --get ComputerName&lt;/code&gt;. The sparsebundle &amp;lsquo;file&amp;rsquo; is really a directory, and the script creates an XML plist file inside it, and then copies it to &lt;code&gt;/your/network/share/name.sparsebundle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-3&#34;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to mount the sparsebundle file, all you have to do is open the file, and it will mount as &lt;code&gt;/Volumes/Time Machine Backups&lt;/code&gt;, then run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;./3_set_destination.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And enter your password if it prompts you. If you are uncomfortable blindly running scripts as super-user, I understand, read the script to make sure you know what you it is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explanation:&lt;/em&gt; This script uses the Time Machine utility, &lt;code&gt;tmutil&lt;/code&gt; to set the Time Machine destination to the &lt;code&gt;/Volumes/Time Machine Backups&lt;/code&gt; mount point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can fire up Time Machine and start your backups!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History of Domain Names</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/06/history-of-domain-names/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/06/history-of-domain-names/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In trying to understand &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_Name_System&#34;&gt;DNS&lt;/a&gt; better, I stumbled upon this little bit of history in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1034.txt&#34;&gt;RFC 1034&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RFC 1034             Domain Concepts and Facilities        November 1987&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.1. The history of domain names&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impetus for the development of the domain system was growth in the
Internet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host name to address mappings were maintained by the Network
 Information Center (NIC) in a single file (HOSTS.TXT) which
 was FTPed by all hosts [RFC-952, RFC-953].  The total network
 bandwidth consumed in distributing a new version by this
 scheme is proportional to the square of the number of hosts in
 the network, and even when multiple levels of FTP are used,
 the outgoing FTP load on the NIC host is considerable.
 Explosive growth in the number of hosts didn&amp;rsquo;t bode well for
 the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, there used to be a single file that mapped hostnames to IP addresses, and everyone on the network would fetch that file over ftp to stay up to date with the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain the quadratic growth (proportional to the square of the number of hosts), &lt;a href=&#34;https://self-evident.org/&#34;&gt;Nemo&lt;/a&gt; corrected my explanation with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the size of the HOSTS.TXT file is linear in the number of hosts, and the number of hosts that need to download the file is also linear in the number of hosts, therefore the total bandwidth required to distribute the file to all hosts is quadratic in the number of hosts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>