<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Howto on tlehman@home</title>
    <link>/categories/howto/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Howto on tlehman@home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/howto/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Point Time Machine at any destination</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/12/08/point-time-machine-at-any-destination/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/12/08/point-time-machine-at-any-destination/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;set-up-time-machine-on-mac-os-x-to-back-up-to-any-network-volume&#34;&gt;Set up Time Machine (on Mac OS X) to back up to any network volume&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time Machine is a fine backup solution if you have a dedicated external hard drive, or if you have no problem with paying for a specialized Time Capsule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a network volume, such as an NFS, CIFS, AFP, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/philipl/pifs#readme&#34;&gt;πfs&lt;/a&gt; share on a file server, you need to configure a few things in order for Time Machine to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/5691649/an-easier-way-to-set-up-time-machine-to-back-up-to-a-networked-windows-computer&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; which gives step-by-step instructions, but it involves executing some shell commands. I&amp;rsquo;ve distilled it into three scripts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1_enable_network_volumes.sh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2_make_image.sh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3_set_destination.sh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-1&#34;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clone &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tlehman/time_machine_any_destination&#34;&gt;this repository&lt;/a&gt;, and execute this script by cd-ing to the repository&amp;rsquo;s directory, and run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;./1_enable_network_volumes.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explanation:&lt;/em&gt; This enables unsupported network volumes by setting &lt;code&gt;TMShowUnsupportedNetworkVolumes&lt;/code&gt; to 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-2&#34;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, you need to prepare a special directory on your network share, this second script will do that for you. Make sure you have your network share &lt;code&gt;/your/network/share&lt;/code&gt; ready, and choose a maximum number of gigabytes, say &lt;code&gt;216&lt;/code&gt;, and run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;./2_make_image.sh 216 /your/network/share
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning&lt;/strong&gt;: This script will take a while, you&amp;rsquo;ll know when it&amp;rsquo;s done when you &lt;code&gt;Finished! Happy backups!&lt;/code&gt; in your terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explanation&lt;/em&gt;: This script creates a disk image &lt;code&gt;name.sparsebundle&lt;/code&gt;, where name is your computer name, the result of the command &lt;code&gt;scutil --get ComputerName&lt;/code&gt;. The sparsebundle &amp;lsquo;file&amp;rsquo; is really a directory, and the script creates an XML plist file inside it, and then copies it to &lt;code&gt;/your/network/share/name.sparsebundle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-3&#34;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to mount the sparsebundle file, all you have to do is open the file, and it will mount as &lt;code&gt;/Volumes/Time Machine Backups&lt;/code&gt;, then run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;./3_set_destination.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And enter your password if it prompts you. If you are uncomfortable blindly running scripts as super-user, I understand, read the script to make sure you know what you it is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explanation:&lt;/em&gt; This script uses the Time Machine utility, &lt;code&gt;tmutil&lt;/code&gt; to set the Time Machine destination to the &lt;code&gt;/Volumes/Time Machine Backups&lt;/code&gt; mount point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can fire up Time Machine and start your backups!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extract array of frames from mp4 using Python OpenCV bindings</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/01/20/extract-array-of-frames-from-mp4-using-python-opencv-bindings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/01/20/extract-array-of-frames-from-mp4-using-python-opencv-bindings/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;OpenCV is a mature Computer Vision library written in C++. There are python bindings available that make working with the library very convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To extract the frames from an mp4 file using the Python OpenCV bindings, you first need python, and the &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; package manager for python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, you will need a system package manager such as Portage for Gentoo Linux or Homebrew for Mac OS X. You will need to compile OpenCV with your specific python version, for this example I am using python 2.7, you can find out which version you have by running &lt;code&gt;python --version&lt;/code&gt;. This example will use Mac OS X 10.8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;install-ffmpeg&#34;&gt;Install ffmpeg&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew install ffmpeg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-opencv-with-python2-7-and-ffmpeg&#34;&gt;Build OpenCV with Python2.7 and ffmpeg&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew install opencv --python27 --ffmpeg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am taking the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/images&#34;&gt;Coursera Image and Video processing&lt;/a&gt; class right now, the example file I am using is one of &lt;a href=&#34;https://class.coursera.org/images-2012-001/lecture/download.mp4?lecture_id=7&#34;&gt;the lectures&lt;/a&gt;, I saved the file as &lt;code&gt;course-logistics.mp4&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use OpenCV in python, you need to import cv2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;import cv2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, to open the video file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;vidcap = cv2.VideoCapture(&#39;course-logistics.mp4&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to extract frames is to use the &lt;code&gt;read()&lt;/code&gt; method on the vidcap object. It returns a &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.python.org/2/tutorial/datastructures.html#tuples-and-sequences&#34;&gt;tuple&lt;/a&gt; where the first element is a success flag and the second is the image array. To extract the image array:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;success,image = vidcap.read()
# image is an array of array of [R,G,B] values
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To convert the whole video to frames and save each one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;count = 0; 
while success:
	success,image = vidcap.read()
	cv2.imwrite(&amp;quot;frame%d.jpg&amp;quot; % count, image)     # save frame as JPEG file
	if cv2.waitKey(10) == 27:                     # exit if Escape is hit
    	break
	count += 1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above loop runs until &lt;code&gt;success&lt;/code&gt; is false or the user hits the Escape key. Each iteration saves the current frame as a JPEG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one way to extract a sequence of frames from a movie. Another way would be to change the body of the above while loop to do something else.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>