<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>time-travel on tobilehman.com:~</title>
    <link>https://tobilehman.com/tags/time-travel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in time-travel on tobilehman.com:~</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2010-2022 Tobi Lehman. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 21:10:35 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://tobilehman.com/tags/time-travel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Time Loops</title>
      <link>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-time-loops/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 21:10:35 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-time-loops/</guid>
      <description>The book Time Loops by Eric Wargo makes a careful argument for the reality of precognitive dreams.
My personal interest in this topic has to do with my obsession with time and to an extent, time travel.
The author starts the book by summarizing a number of examples of dreams that came true, and closely studies an early dream pioneer named J.W. Dunne who wrote An Experiment with Time. What stands out about Dunne is how he made the distinction between dreaming about events out in the world vs events as experienced by the future self.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Topology of Time Travel Stories</title>
      <link>https://tobilehman.com/posts/time-travel-topology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 20:53:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tobilehman.com/posts/time-travel-topology/</guid>
      <description>Everyone needs an obscure useless skill. ‐ @Noahpinion
Mine is identifying the topology of time travel stories.
Click here if you know what topology is and just want to get to the time travel stuff
a brief introduction to topology The original study of shapes was geometry, popularized by a Greek mathematician named Euclid. Starting about 2000 years after that, a Swiss mathematician named Euler (pronounced &amp;ldquo;Oiler&amp;rdquo;) accidentally inventented topology while trying to solve the Seven Bridges of Königsberg problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time Travel Rules in Movies</title>
      <link>https://tobilehman.com/posts/time-travel-rules-movies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 15:59:10 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tobilehman.com/posts/time-travel-rules-movies/</guid>
      <description>I mapped out the rules of various time travel movies:
Here&amp;rsquo;s the source code for the graphviz file.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
