<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>History on tlehman@home</title>
    <link>/categories/history/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in History on tlehman@home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Review: The Warmth of Other Suns by Isabel Wilkerson</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/08/04/review-the-warmth-of-other-suns-by-isabel-wilkerson/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/08/04/review-the-warmth-of-other-suns-by-isabel-wilkerson/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Isabel Wilkerson&amp;rsquo;s riveting book about the Great Migration of African-Americans out of the south is the perfect blend of narrative and statisitcs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;float: right; width: 50%&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/images/books/warmth_of_other_suns.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The personal stories of Ida Mae Brandon Gladney, George Swanson Starling and Robert Joseph Pershing Foster are the substantive bulk of the book. Around these personal stories are statistics that serve to add context and clarity to a movement that was so large, and took place over a long enough time, that it&amp;rsquo;s easy to miss it as a distinct historical period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book was my introduction to the Great Migration. It was a migration that began in 1915 with World War 1 and ended around 1970. Nearly 6 million African Americans left the South and traveled to cities in the North or the West, such as New York, Chicago, Baltimore, Cleveland, Los Angeles and Oakland. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t a coordinated effort, it was the result of large economic and social forces, as well as millions of personal decisions to leave a part of the United States that historically had treated black people as property, and hadn&amp;rsquo;t improved much since the end of the civil war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several decades after the end of the civil war, even though slavery had been abolished, the old social order still existed, the same industries existed. Slavery had been replaced with the slightly less bad, but still quite terrible practice of sharecropping, where white planation owners would hire former slaves and children of former slaves as laborers. They usually took advantage of the fact that the black workers weren&amp;rsquo;t educated, effectively getting free or near-free labor. The de facto segregation that existed quickly became de jure segregation with the passing of Jim Crow laws in most southern states and counties. This began to change in a big way during World War 1, since the men that left for war in the north left a labor vacuum. Recruiters from the north would go south, trying to convince many black residents in the south to move north for jobs. This was just the beginning, since the family and friends of those first migrants kept that route in their minds as a possible option for a better life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book proceeds by moving through three parallel timelines, one of Ida Mae, a sharecropper&amp;rsquo;s wife from Missippi, who left in the 1930s. Then George Starling, a fruit picker from Florida, and finally Robert Foster, from Lousiana. The stories are told in parallel, but they all take place about a decade apart from one another. Wilkerson&amp;rsquo;s narrative style is so good, I sometimes felt like the stories were happening in the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In between the personal stories were discussions relevant statistics, such as how many people had left which state, and incomes of black teachers and white teachers that were similarly qualified. The book does doesn&amp;rsquo;t just steep the reader in data, it moves briskly back into narrative and continues the unfolding saga of the three brave migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two parts of the book that stood out most to me, one having to do with wealth inequality:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In neighboring Mississippi, white teachers and principals were making $630 a year, while the colored ones were paid a third of that-$215 a year, hardly more than field hands. But knowing that didn&amp;rsquo;t ease the burden of the Foster&amp;rsquo;s lives, get their children through college, or allow them to build assets to match their status and education.
The disparity in pay, reported without apology in the local papers for all to see, would have far-reaching effects. It would mean that the most promising of colored people, having received next to nothing in material assets from their slave foreparents, had to labor with the knowledge that they were now being underpaid by more than half, that they were so behind it would be all but impossible to accumulate the assets their white counterparts could, and that they would, by definition, have less to leave succeeding generations than similar white families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was followed by the long term consequences, which influence the world of today (2015):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiplied over the generations, it would mean a wealth deficit between the races that would require a miracle windfall or near aceticism on the part of colored families if they were to have any chance of catching up or amassing anything of value. Otherwise, the chasm would continue, as it did for blacks as a group even into the succeeding century. The layers of accumulated assets built up by the better-paid dominant caste, generation after generation, would factor into a wealth disparity of white Americans having an average net worth ten times that of black Americans by the turn of the twenty-first century, dampening the economic prospects of the children and grandchildren of the Great Migration before they were even born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This explanation clarified the concept of white privilege to me better than anything I&amp;rsquo;ve seen before, or since. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s gotten slightly worse since the turn of the century, a recent Pew Research study found that the average net worth of white families is thirteen times that of the average black family:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.pewresearch.org/files/2014/12/FT_14.12.11_wealthGap2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other part that stood out to me was about automation and jobs, the story about &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_unemployment&#34;&gt;technological unemployment&lt;/a&gt; usually goes: &lt;em&gt;first a new technology emerges that makes some kind of human labor obsolete, and then those laborers lose their jobs, and get replaced by machines&lt;/em&gt;. While there are many examples of this, reality is much more complicated. Here&amp;rsquo;s the quote from the book related to this topic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took World War II and the even bigger outflow of blacks to awaken them to what some agricultural engineers working on a mechanical harvester already knew: &amp;ldquo;Much of this labor is not returning to the farm,&amp;rdquo; Harris P. Smith, the chief of agricultural engineering at Texas A&amp;amp;M University, wrote in 1946. &amp;ldquo;Therefore, the cotton farmer is forced to mechanize.&amp;rdquo; As for the connection between the Migration and the machine, Smith concluded that &amp;ldquo;instead of the machines displacing labor, they were used to replace the labor that had left the farm&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of cotton picking in the south, automation didn&amp;rsquo;t destroy jobs, it filled in a void of jobs that people willingly left. This aligns with my ideas about what kinds of work should be replaced by machines. Anything repetitive and degrading should be done by a machine. Humans are too important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is well worth your time, it is very informative, eye-opening, and incredibly well written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Wilkerson, Isabel. The Warmth of Other Suns: The Epic Story of America&amp;rsquo;s Great Migration. New York, NY: Random House, 2010. Print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] Wealth inequality has widened along racial, ethnic lines since end of Great Recession &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2014/12/12/racial-wealth-gaps-great-recession/&#34;&gt;http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2014/12/12/racial-wealth-gaps-great-recession/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modular computing forever?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/31/modular-computing-forever/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/31/modular-computing-forever/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I remember building my first computer, I was about 14, I ordered my AMD Athlon XP processor, got a motherboard and case, keyboard, monitor, sound card, graphics card, etc. All that. Assembling it was straighforward, but configuring it was a challenge, getting GNU/Linux and Windows 2000 to dual boot, then getting drivers straight, setting up a shared partition for data sharing. It was rewarding to get it all up and running. I upgraded that computer piece by piece, getting a new graphics card, hard drive, keyboard/mouse, RAM, CPU and eventually a new motherboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had that computer all the way through high school and afterward, because the pieces used standard interfaces like PCI, AGP, Socket A, USB etc. I could replace individual components as I needed, without having to buy a whole new system. This was (and in my opinion is) what all hardware should aspire to. I define modularity not only by the ability to swap out components, but also to have components that are interoperable (e.g. my RAM works in an AMD or an Intel box).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, it seems obvious that interoperability is ideal. It&amp;rsquo;s good for the consumer, but it makes sense why there are lots of proprietary connectors and non-interoperable devices, because of the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the standard must exist (e.g. USB, Socket A)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the standard must have features that intersect with the goals of the device manufacturer (e.g. USB 2.0 is not fast enough for use with your main hard drive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the manufacturer must comply with the standard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem was explored in &lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/927/&#34;&gt;XKCD 927: Standards&lt;/a&gt;, there may be a standard, but it&amp;rsquo;s not unique, leading to fragmentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these challenges, modular personal computers exist. This ideal of modularity has not been realized very much in the mobile computer space though, tablets and phones are selling like crazy, and they all are more or less out-of-the-box, sealed devices with little hope of swapping out parts. iPhones, iPads, Nexus phones and tablets have difficult to replace batteries (usually voiding a warranty in the process). I&amp;rsquo;ve broken an iPhone 4 trying to replace the lock button, this is because the parts are too small. Also, none of the parts are interoperable, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t take a Nexus 4 battery and replace it with an iPhone 5 battery, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I would like to point out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifixit.com/&#34;&gt;ifixit.com&lt;/a&gt;, they have great tutorials on fixing phones and tablets, and are a remedy to the current situation of devices that are difficult to work on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to complain though, I love iPhones, Nexus phones and tablets, they are compact, convenient and very useful for most of non-work related casual computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was naturally very excited to hear about Motorola Ara:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/blogimg/moto_ara.jpg %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a project that aims to make a set of modular components that can be combined to build your own phone, and swap out parts as needed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought that this could be the beginning of a golden age of mobile computer interoperability, as consumers would flock to this platform because of the economic benefit of being able to replace parts as needed. I later realized this might be a fantasy, after reading a &lt;a href=&#34;http://jjcm.org/blog/mac_pros_and_modularity/&#34;&gt;good article by Jacob Miller&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jacob argues that non-modularity is inevitable, for more than the four reasons I mentioned above, I urge you to read the article, it&amp;rsquo;s very well written and thoughtful, but until then I&amp;rsquo;ll include the quote that for me was an inflection point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all these changes in speed, one thing has largely stayed nearly the same. &lt;strong&gt;The physical size of the interconnect is still limited not by our current technology, but by our ability as humans to line up copper connectors&lt;/strong&gt;. Right now the lane size for PCI Express is the exact same as it was back in 1993 when PCI was released - 1mm. Contrast that with the lane size in a modern day processor - currently 22nm. Eventually, we&amp;rsquo;re going to hit a limit with the amount of data that any individual lane can transfer (currently at a jaw dropping 1969MB/s with PCI-E v.4), simply because we can only bend the laws of physics so far. At that point, our only option to increase speed is going to be to add more lanes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that point, modularity will begin to fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His article clarified a choice that hardware designers and manufacturers have to make, &lt;em&gt;increase speed and capacity while shrinking the device, or preserve the ability for humans to operate on the parts, and replace them as needed&lt;/em&gt;. On the iPhone side, the former was chosen, on the Motorola Ara side, the latter was chosen, and as a result, Ara phones will necessarily be bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As parts get smaller, the very ability for us humans to swap out those parts diminishes. Devices like the iPhone 4 and 5 are so compact that it&amp;rsquo;s just really hard to even get to the parts. This trend is likely to continue, and the preference for smaller devices may lead to the failure of Project Ara.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to give Ara a try, and I hope that it succeeds, but I no longer believe everyone will flock to it, because Apple, LG and Samsung will keep making smaller and smaller devices that sacrifice modularity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History of Domain Names</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/06/history-of-domain-names/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/06/history-of-domain-names/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In trying to understand &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_Name_System&#34;&gt;DNS&lt;/a&gt; better, I stumbled upon this little bit of history in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1034.txt&#34;&gt;RFC 1034&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RFC 1034             Domain Concepts and Facilities        November 1987&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.1. The history of domain names&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impetus for the development of the domain system was growth in the
Internet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host name to address mappings were maintained by the Network
 Information Center (NIC) in a single file (HOSTS.TXT) which
 was FTPed by all hosts [RFC-952, RFC-953].  The total network
 bandwidth consumed in distributing a new version by this
 scheme is proportional to the square of the number of hosts in
 the network, and even when multiple levels of FTP are used,
 the outgoing FTP load on the NIC host is considerable.
 Explosive growth in the number of hosts didn&amp;rsquo;t bode well for
 the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, there used to be a single file that mapped hostnames to IP addresses, and everyone on the network would fetch that file over ftp to stay up to date with the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain the quadratic growth (proportional to the square of the number of hosts), &lt;a href=&#34;https://self-evident.org/&#34;&gt;Nemo&lt;/a&gt; corrected my explanation with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the size of the HOSTS.TXT file is linear in the number of hosts, and the number of hosts that need to download the file is also linear in the number of hosts, therefore the total bandwidth required to distribute the file to all hosts is quadratic in the number of hosts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>