<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Networking on tlehman@home</title>
    <link>/categories/networking/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Networking on tlehman@home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/networking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Country code TLDs using GeoJSON on Github</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/12/28/country-code-tlds-using-geojson-on-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/12/28/country-code-tlds-using-geojson-on-github/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are more country code top-level domains (ccTLDs) than there are countries, that is because territories such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wallis_and_Futuna&#34;&gt;Wallis and Futuna&lt;/a&gt; has the ccTLD &lt;code&gt;.wf&lt;/code&gt;, even though it&amp;rsquo;s a French territory, not a country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many that I have a hard time remembering them, and given one it&amp;rsquo;s hard to tell what country it belongs to, since &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iso.org/iso/country_codes&#34;&gt;ISO 3166&lt;/a&gt; specifies that ccTLDs should be two characters long, that makes a maximum of 676 (26 squared) ccTLDs that could ever exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve the ccTLD→(Country/Territory)  problem, there is this great decoding table &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iso.org/iso/home/standards/country_codes/iso-3166-1_decoding_table.htm&#34;&gt;here at iso.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the other problem, (Country/Territory)→ccTLD, I made the following map using &lt;a href=&#34;http://geojson.org/&#34;&gt;GeoJSON&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/tlehman/8166180.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History of Domain Names</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/06/history-of-domain-names/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/06/history-of-domain-names/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In trying to understand &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_Name_System&#34;&gt;DNS&lt;/a&gt; better, I stumbled upon this little bit of history in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1034.txt&#34;&gt;RFC 1034&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RFC 1034             Domain Concepts and Facilities        November 1987&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.1. The history of domain names&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impetus for the development of the domain system was growth in the
Internet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host name to address mappings were maintained by the Network
 Information Center (NIC) in a single file (HOSTS.TXT) which
 was FTPed by all hosts [RFC-952, RFC-953].  The total network
 bandwidth consumed in distributing a new version by this
 scheme is proportional to the square of the number of hosts in
 the network, and even when multiple levels of FTP are used,
 the outgoing FTP load on the NIC host is considerable.
 Explosive growth in the number of hosts didn&amp;rsquo;t bode well for
 the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, there used to be a single file that mapped hostnames to IP addresses, and everyone on the network would fetch that file over ftp to stay up to date with the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain the quadratic growth (proportional to the square of the number of hosts), &lt;a href=&#34;https://self-evident.org/&#34;&gt;Nemo&lt;/a&gt; corrected my explanation with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the size of the HOSTS.TXT file is linear in the number of hosts, and the number of hosts that need to download the file is also linear in the number of hosts, therefore the total bandwidth required to distribute the file to all hosts is quadratic in the number of hosts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>