<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Race on tlehman@home</title>
    <link>/categories/race/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Race on tlehman@home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/race/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Review: The Warmth of Other Suns by Isabel Wilkerson</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/08/04/review-the-warmth-of-other-suns-by-isabel-wilkerson/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/08/04/review-the-warmth-of-other-suns-by-isabel-wilkerson/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Isabel Wilkerson&amp;rsquo;s riveting book about the Great Migration of African-Americans out of the south is the perfect blend of narrative and statisitcs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;float: right; width: 50%&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/images/books/warmth_of_other_suns.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The personal stories of Ida Mae Brandon Gladney, George Swanson Starling and Robert Joseph Pershing Foster are the substantive bulk of the book. Around these personal stories are statistics that serve to add context and clarity to a movement that was so large, and took place over a long enough time, that it&amp;rsquo;s easy to miss it as a distinct historical period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book was my introduction to the Great Migration. It was a migration that began in 1915 with World War 1 and ended around 1970. Nearly 6 million African Americans left the South and traveled to cities in the North or the West, such as New York, Chicago, Baltimore, Cleveland, Los Angeles and Oakland. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t a coordinated effort, it was the result of large economic and social forces, as well as millions of personal decisions to leave a part of the United States that historically had treated black people as property, and hadn&amp;rsquo;t improved much since the end of the civil war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several decades after the end of the civil war, even though slavery had been abolished, the old social order still existed, the same industries existed. Slavery had been replaced with the slightly less bad, but still quite terrible practice of sharecropping, where white planation owners would hire former slaves and children of former slaves as laborers. They usually took advantage of the fact that the black workers weren&amp;rsquo;t educated, effectively getting free or near-free labor. The de facto segregation that existed quickly became de jure segregation with the passing of Jim Crow laws in most southern states and counties. This began to change in a big way during World War 1, since the men that left for war in the north left a labor vacuum. Recruiters from the north would go south, trying to convince many black residents in the south to move north for jobs. This was just the beginning, since the family and friends of those first migrants kept that route in their minds as a possible option for a better life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book proceeds by moving through three parallel timelines, one of Ida Mae, a sharecropper&amp;rsquo;s wife from Missippi, who left in the 1930s. Then George Starling, a fruit picker from Florida, and finally Robert Foster, from Lousiana. The stories are told in parallel, but they all take place about a decade apart from one another. Wilkerson&amp;rsquo;s narrative style is so good, I sometimes felt like the stories were happening in the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In between the personal stories were discussions relevant statistics, such as how many people had left which state, and incomes of black teachers and white teachers that were similarly qualified. The book does doesn&amp;rsquo;t just steep the reader in data, it moves briskly back into narrative and continues the unfolding saga of the three brave migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two parts of the book that stood out most to me, one having to do with wealth inequality:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In neighboring Mississippi, white teachers and principals were making $630 a year, while the colored ones were paid a third of that-$215 a year, hardly more than field hands. But knowing that didn&amp;rsquo;t ease the burden of the Foster&amp;rsquo;s lives, get their children through college, or allow them to build assets to match their status and education.
The disparity in pay, reported without apology in the local papers for all to see, would have far-reaching effects. It would mean that the most promising of colored people, having received next to nothing in material assets from their slave foreparents, had to labor with the knowledge that they were now being underpaid by more than half, that they were so behind it would be all but impossible to accumulate the assets their white counterparts could, and that they would, by definition, have less to leave succeeding generations than similar white families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was followed by the long term consequences, which influence the world of today (2015):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiplied over the generations, it would mean a wealth deficit between the races that would require a miracle windfall or near aceticism on the part of colored families if they were to have any chance of catching up or amassing anything of value. Otherwise, the chasm would continue, as it did for blacks as a group even into the succeeding century. The layers of accumulated assets built up by the better-paid dominant caste, generation after generation, would factor into a wealth disparity of white Americans having an average net worth ten times that of black Americans by the turn of the twenty-first century, dampening the economic prospects of the children and grandchildren of the Great Migration before they were even born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This explanation clarified the concept of white privilege to me better than anything I&amp;rsquo;ve seen before, or since. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s gotten slightly worse since the turn of the century, a recent Pew Research study found that the average net worth of white families is thirteen times that of the average black family:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.pewresearch.org/files/2014/12/FT_14.12.11_wealthGap2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other part that stood out to me was about automation and jobs, the story about &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_unemployment&#34;&gt;technological unemployment&lt;/a&gt; usually goes: &lt;em&gt;first a new technology emerges that makes some kind of human labor obsolete, and then those laborers lose their jobs, and get replaced by machines&lt;/em&gt;. While there are many examples of this, reality is much more complicated. Here&amp;rsquo;s the quote from the book related to this topic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took World War II and the even bigger outflow of blacks to awaken them to what some agricultural engineers working on a mechanical harvester already knew: &amp;ldquo;Much of this labor is not returning to the farm,&amp;rdquo; Harris P. Smith, the chief of agricultural engineering at Texas A&amp;amp;M University, wrote in 1946. &amp;ldquo;Therefore, the cotton farmer is forced to mechanize.&amp;rdquo; As for the connection between the Migration and the machine, Smith concluded that &amp;ldquo;instead of the machines displacing labor, they were used to replace the labor that had left the farm&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of cotton picking in the south, automation didn&amp;rsquo;t destroy jobs, it filled in a void of jobs that people willingly left. This aligns with my ideas about what kinds of work should be replaced by machines. Anything repetitive and degrading should be done by a machine. Humans are too important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is well worth your time, it is very informative, eye-opening, and incredibly well written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Wilkerson, Isabel. The Warmth of Other Suns: The Epic Story of America&amp;rsquo;s Great Migration. New York, NY: Random House, 2010. Print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] Wealth inequality has widened along racial, ethnic lines since end of Great Recession &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2014/12/12/racial-wealth-gaps-great-recession/&#34;&gt;http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2014/12/12/racial-wealth-gaps-great-recession/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>