<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>finance on tobilehman.com:~</title>
    <link>https://tobilehman.com/tags/finance/</link>
    <description>Recent content in finance on tobilehman.com:~</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2010-2024 Tobi Lehman. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 06:45:23 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://tobilehman.com/tags/finance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Technological Revolutions and Financial Capital</title>
      <link>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-perez-trfc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 06:45:23 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobilehman.com/posts/book-review-perez-trfc/</guid>
      <description>This book develops a theory of a cyclical pattern in the economy. The pattern describes how certain new technologies spread to become a whole new way of structuring society. The author Carlota Perez calls this a technological revolution and it&amp;rsquo;s associated &amp;ldquo;techno-economic paradigm&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;In this review I want to summarize her theory using less jargon. Even though the book reads like an academic text, and the jargon is used consistently, I want to dig into the idea in more common language.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ads, Subscriptions, and the Missing Middle</title>
      <link>https://tobilehman.com/posts/ads-subscriptions-and-the-missing-middle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2020 20:21:15 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobilehman.com/posts/ads-subscriptions-and-the-missing-middle/</guid>
      <description>Publishers need to make a living. Journalists, video producers, musicians, and bloggers all have to pay their bills.&#xA;The two common ways of making money from online content are:&#xA;Free content with ads Subscription content without ads Sometimes publishers use both, but with a reduced number of ads for subscribers, magazine-style.&#xA;The trouble with subscriptions is that people can quickly feel saturated. Once you subscribe to WaPo, NYTimes, WSJ, you might want to read that LATimes article, but don&amp;rsquo;t want to sign up for yet another monthly subscription.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
