<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Logic on tlehman@home</title>
    <link>/categories/logic/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Logic on tlehman@home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/logic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Logical consistency in Law</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/10/27/logical-consistency-in-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/10/27/logical-consistency-in-law/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Washington state has two contradictory initiatives on the ballot this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initiative 591 (I-591) would prevent background checks for gun purchases except when required by the federal government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initiative 594 (I-594) would ensure background checks for all gun purchases, including those conducted online and at gun shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/background-checks-for-gun-sales-look-likely-to-pass-in-washington/&#34;&gt;FiveThirtyEight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of thing shouldn&amp;rsquo;t even be let onto the ballot. There should be something akin to a compiler that can weed out laws that are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contradictory to one another&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contradictory to existing law&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first requirement is easy, the second requirement is harder, I mentioned it &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/09/14/viewing-nsa-accountability-act-amendments-as-a-diff/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Courts do serve this role, but only after laws are passed and people contest it. I think there is still room for cleaning the process up a bit and weeding out mutually contradictory laws that show up on the same ballot!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lies Damned Lies and Statistics</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/04/03/lies-damned-lies-and-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/04/03/lies-damned-lies-and-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a quote, usually attributed to Mark Twain that goes something
like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There are three kinds lies.
Lies, Damned Lies, and Statistics.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My interpretation of this is that statistics are supposed to be the
worst kind of lie, or that the worst kinds of lies use
statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing that bothers me most about this quote (and the innumerable
minor variations of it that get repeated) is that the word
&amp;lsquo;statistics&amp;rsquo; comes at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does that matter? Notice that the list is presented as a sequence,
an increasing sequence of damned-ness, and the presence of the word
&amp;lsquo;statistics&amp;rsquo; at the end is supposed to imply that it is &amp;lsquo;more damned&amp;rsquo;
than damned lies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interpretation bothers me because the implied damned-ness is
based on the initial correlation, and that correlation is only based
on two data points. The quote depends on a misunderstanding of
statistics. Anyone who has studied a little bit of statistics will
know not to trust an inference based on a correlation in a data set
of only two points!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>