<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Csv on tlehman@home</title>
    <link>/categories/csv/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Csv on tlehman@home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/csv/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>White House releases first ever open source budget proposal</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/02/03/white-house-releases-first-ever-open-source-budget-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/02/03/white-house-releases-first-ever-open-source-budget-proposal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The White House just released the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/WhiteHouse/2016-budget-data&#34;&gt;first ever open source budget proposal&lt;/a&gt;. It is released on GitHub, and it&amp;rsquo;s a bunch of CSV files. This is not very difficult, it requires only a few extra clicks when exporting an Excel spreadsheet, but hosting it on GitHub also opens it up to &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/articles/using-pull-requests/&#34;&gt;Pull Requests&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/09/14/viewing-nsa-accountability-act-amendments-as-a-diff/&#34;&gt;talked about before&lt;/a&gt; as being a much better tool for 21st century democracy. Instead of paper and a bunch of politicians in a room following procedure, we should intead have a digital system where all citizens can contribute as easily as they can update a facebook status or apply an instagram filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One huge caveat is in order though: there is no reason to assume that the White House and Congress will even consider pull requests, let alone apply them. This aside, I will experiment with this, I&amp;rsquo;ve already modified &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dinedal/textql/pull/39&#34;&gt;textql&lt;/a&gt; so that I can easily query these CSV files from a SQLite database. If I have an idea about how I&amp;rsquo;d like to change the budget, I&amp;rsquo;ll submit the pull request and then follow it&amp;rsquo;s response, if any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caveats aside, I am impressed with the choice of technologies for making these public issues more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>